My chakra is reacting strongly.
What's that?
It's what was growing on
the sick people.
(アシュラ)俺のチャクラが
すごく反応してる。
I see!
The sap from the Divine Tree's
seeped into the soil.
(カンナ)これは？
The sap acts like a fertilizer,
(アシュラ)さっきの病人たちに
生えていたのは これだ。
making this area a lush oasis in
the middle of such a barren region.
そうか 神樹の樹液が
大地に染み出してるんだ。
The power of the Divine Tree
is making the land fertile?
たぶん この樹液が栄養となり→
So... is the Divine Tree
getting its power back?
荒野のど真ん中に オアシスを
作り出してるんだ。
No, it hasn't completely revived...
(タイゾウ)神樹の力が土地を
豊かにしてるってのか？
But it probably will eventually.
うん。
それじゃ 神樹は→
力を取り戻してきてる？
いや。
But the real problem is...
まだ完全に
蘇生してるわけじゃない。
Is what?
The people are becoming
contaminated first.
でも 徐々によみがえるだろうね。
Contaminated?!
問題は それより…。
The people and animals eat
the produce grown on this land,
何だよ？
which accumulates
the sap of the Divine Tree.
人間のほうが先に
汚染されると思う。
So does that mean...
汚染？
ああ 神樹の樹液は→
If you eat the food here,
you're gonna get sick?
この地の作物から
それを食べる動物や人間に→
Probably.
But I ate so much yesterday!
どんどん蓄積される。
ってことは→
It's all right. My jutsu can
take care of a small amount...
ここの食い物食うと
あの病気にかかるってことかよ。
たぶん。
オエッ！
But if you keep ingesting and
accumulating it for many years...
俺 昨日 思いっきり
食っちまったぜ！
大丈夫だよ 少しくらいなら
俺の術でも治せる。
Since the Village Elder ordered
for this place to be under watch,
でも 長年 蓄積されたものは…。
does that means
he knows everything?
でもよ ここの警備を
長老がやらせてたってことは→
So it seems.
長老は全部 知ってる
ってことじゃねえのか？
そうなるね。
aimaina hyouden koshiraete hitatteru no
I create a vague critical biography and wallow in it
seisei saisai nani o mada matteru no
Generation after generation, time after time,
what are you still waiting for
itsunomanika hitori ni natta
I was all alone before I knew it
tameiki hitotsu haite nageite
Breathed out a single sigh and lamented
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosunda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
en de tsunagareba kono hibi mo
Bind these days with bonds and perhaps
suteru hodo koware tenaidarou
They can be salvaged
ayumi o tomenaide
Don't stop walking forward
kibou o sutenaide
Don't give up hope
douka furimuite
Please look back
dou ka kimiyo
Please, if you would
jin jin kokoro ga itamunara
If the heart throbs with pain
kannen no ori o uchiyaburu nda
Break through the ideology that imprisons you
enen tsukihi wa megurukedo
Time goes around for eternity
suteru ni wa yami ga asaidarou
But the darkness within you is still shallow,
not worth throwing it all away
jounetsu moyashita ano koro o
Those days of burning passion
shinketsu sosoide torimodosu nda
Put your heart and soul into getting them back
ai o wakeaeba kono hibi mo
If we love each other then surely these days will
mouichido kimi o terasudarou
Once again, shine upon you
Ashura's Decision
I see...
You saw the Divine Tree.
Yes.
Traveler, why do you keep digging
for our village secrets?
そうか 神樹を見たのか。
はい。
Forgive me.
I'm from the Village of Ninshu
and was told to come here.
旅の者よ なぜお前は
そこまで村の秘密を探るのだ？
Ninshu?
The Ninshu that destroyed
the land 20 years ago...
すみません 実は俺→
You are a pupil?
忍宗の里から ここへ
来るように言われたんです。
Yes.
That tree is the ruin of the specter
that almost destroyed our world.
忍宗？
20年前 大地を滅ぼしたという…。
That is why it's so powerful.
お前は その一門か？
はい。
I've been ordered to do
something about it.
あの樹は
地上を破滅に追いやった→
Lord Elder, to be blunt,
that tree is a narcotic.
もののけの残骸です
だから 力があるのです。
The power of the Divine Tree is
indeed making this land abundant,
私は それをなんとかするように
言いつかってきました。
but it's also affecting
the villagers adversely.
長老 いわば あの樹は麻薬です。
At this rate...
神樹の力は確かに
土地を豊かにします。
Traveler,
I am already aware of that.
ですが 同時に村人たちを
蝕んでもいる。
But I cannot authorize
that tree's destruction.
このままでは いずれ…。
Why is that?
旅の者よ それは
気づいていたことじゃ。
That tree started to grow powerfully
several decades ago.
だが あの樹をなくすことは→
Until then,
this was arid and barren land.
許可できぬ。
なぜです？
あの樹が力を持ち始めたのは→
We had terrible droughts
nearly every year.
今から十数年ほど前じゃ。
I've lost count of how many
died of starvation.
それまで この地は
荒れ果てた土地じゃった。
Why don't you try digging a well?
It was futile...
容赦ない干ばつが
毎年のように襲い→
"Was"?
We tried ages ago.
数え切れぬほどの
餓死者を出してきた。
One could dig for years,
だったら 井戸を掘ってみては？
only to hit the solid bedrock
that runs across this land.
ムダだった。
だった？
とっくにそんなことは試した。
If we cut down that tree now,
what will happen to us?
だが 何年掘ろうと
この土地に横たわる固い岩盤が→
I cannot tell the villagers
that we will be returning to
those days of hunger and suffering.
それを拒んでおるのだ。
今 あの樹を失えば
我々は どうなる？
Besides, even if I told them the truth,
the villagers will not believe me.
村の者たちに
飢えに怯える日々に戻れなど→
Traveler, do not get involved
any further...
わしには とうてい言えぬ。
それに たとえ事実を知っても→
It would be best if you leave
as soon as possible.
村人たちは賛同しまい。
旅の者よ わしらに
これ以上 かかわるな。
Kanna, how do you feel?
早々にこの地を立ち去るがよい。
About what?
In time, you will become infected
by the Divine Tree.
And?
We have no other choice!
カンナ キミはどう思う？
There's nowhere else for us to go!
どう思うって。
キミも このままでは
いつかは神樹に汚染される。
We just have to endure
and live with it.
だからって
どうしようもないじゃない！
Please listen, everyone!
私たちには この土地以外に
行くあてなんてない。
Do you know the truth
behind the Divine Tree?
ただ 我慢するしかないのよ。
Hey, Ashura!
The Divine Tree is
the ruins of a specter.
皆さん 聞いてください。
The Divine Tree is the cause
皆さんは知ってるんですか？
神樹の真実を。
of the illness afflicting
the people at the clinic.
If you continue to rely on
the power of the Divine Tree,
お おいアシュラ。
(アシュラ)神樹は
もののけの残骸です。
you will all fall victim
to the same illness!
療養所の病気の原因は
丘にある神樹なんです。
Are you okay with that?!
Everyone!
神樹の力に頼り続ければ
いずれは みんな同じ病気になる。
Don't listen to this guy!
These two came from
the Village of Ninshu!
They ravaged the world,
皆さんは
それでもいいんですか？
and now, they want to take
the Divine Tree from us!
みんな こいつの話に
耳を貸すな！
We can't let them do that!
Get out of here!
こいつらは忍宗の里から
やってきた連中だ。
What do you think would happen to us
if the Divine Tree was gone?!
世界をボロボロにしたあげくに→
Get lost!
俺たちから神樹様まで
取り上げる気だ！
Ashura, let's get out of here!
そんなこと
させてたまるか！
とっとと帰れ！
神樹様がなくなったら
我々はどうなる？
さっさと出ていけ！
アシュラ逃げよう。
うう。
I hope Masters Indra and Ashura
are all right.
Brother, what kind of places
did you send those two?
(フタミ)大丈夫かな
インドラ様と アシュラ様は。
Simply put, villages burdened
with the same problem.
I want to know how they resolve it.
(ガマ丸)兄弟 いったい２人を
どんな場所にやったんじゃ？
(ハゴロモ)簡単に言えば
同じ問題を抱えている村だ。
I see...
Be honest, have you already decided
which one will succeed you?
それを どう解決するのか
わしは それが知りたいのだ。
No, I haven't decided.
Indra's abilities
are extraordinary,
なるほどのう。
but he is too quick to try to
resolve everything by himself.
正直 もうどちらにするかは
決めているのか？
Ashura is truly kind towards people,
but hesitates to take the lead.
いいや 決めてはいない。
インドラは優秀だが すべてを
１人で解決しようと急ぎすぎる。
If this trip helps them mature
and learn to support each other,
アシュラは
人に対する優しさがあるが→
I would have no complaints.
なかなか
先頭に立とうとはしない。
Gamamaru,
have you had a new dream?
２人が この旅で成長し→
About their futures?
互いに支えあうように
なってくれれば→
If I did have a dream,
would you want me to tell you?
文句はないのだがな。
That would be cheating.
ガマ丸 何か
新しい夢でも見たか？
You must name your successor
by yourself.
２人の未来のことかのう？
見たら教えてほしいのかね？
Well then, I guess I'll be leaving.
それは ズルじゃろ
後継者はお前が自分で決めんと。
Gamamaru, I hope you're
not planning on visiting them...
ゴホン。
よっこら。
Don't interfere.
さて わしは
そろそろ行くかのう。
I won't!
ガマ丸 ２人のところに
行くつもりじゃないだろうな？
ゲコ!?
余計なことはするなよ。
せんわ！
I doubt you all will ever
be able to reach a decision.
しょせん お前たちでは
決断などできないようだな。
Come on Ashura, let's go.
Let's just go and have
a carefree journey.
Uh-huh...
If you're that concerned, just sneak
over there and destroy the tree.
なあアシュラ
もう行こうぜ。
これから気ままな旅に
出たっていいしよ。
You have the power to do that,
don't you?
But then, the villagers will...
う～ん。
そんなに気になるなら あの樹
こっそりぶっ壊しちまえよ！
They'll suffer sure,
but they're going to die eventually.
そのくらい
お前の力でできるだろ！
Oh yeah...
Father didn't say to destroy
the Divine Tree.
でもそれじゃ
村の人たちがな。
Huh?
苦しくはなるけど
いずれ死んじまうんだぜ。
Indra... Ashura...
You will each go to these lands
そうか そういえば
父上は神樹を→
and settle whatever problem
has occurred there.
ただ排除しろとは言わなかったな。
はあ？
Father said to resolve the problem.
((インドラ アシュラ
お前たちは その地に向かい→
Hey, hey... I hope you're
not getting any weird ideas.
(そこで起きている問題を
解決するのだ))
To resolve the problem...
父上は 問題を解決しろ
と言ったんだ。
There's no other way
but to dig a well.
Are you serious?
You heard the old man.
おいおい 何か変なこと
考えてんじゃねえだろうな？
There's solid bedrock and
you can't dig a well.
解決するとしたら やっぱり
井戸を掘るしかないんだ。
Yes... But that time, Father said...
本気か？
長老が言ってたろ？
The power of Ninshu,
which you have inherited...
岩が硬くて
井戸なんて掘れないって。
There is no handbook for its use.
Only you can decide how to use it.
ああ でも父上はあの時
こうも言ったんだ。
((お前たちが授かった忍宗の力→
It's up to us...
その使い方の手本は
どこにもない。
I've decided.
I'm going to do
what I believe is right!
(どう使うかは
お前たちの心しだいなのだ))
Huh?
《俺たちしだい…》
Even if it takes me years!
決めたぜ。
俺は自分の信じることをやる！
It's Master Indra!
はあ？
Master Indra has returned!
何年かかろうと やり遂げる！
Leave it to Master Indra!
He's back already?
インドラ様だ！
I'm glad to see you well.
Where is Ashura?
インドラ様が戻られたぞ！
He's not back yet.
さすがインドラ様だ。
もう戻ってきたのか？
I see...
ハァハァ よくぞご無事で。
アシュラは？
いえ まだ…。
そうか。
Is that—?
Don't tell me he's—?!
あの人は… まさか。
Ashura!
Oh, Kanna!
What are you doing?!
Can't you tell?
I'm digging a well.
ハァハァハァ… アシュラ！
おう カンナ。
何やってるの!?
Are you serious?
Yes.
If you have water, you won't have to
rely on the Divine Tree.
見りゃわかるだろ。
井戸掘ってるんだよ。
That's impossible.
The villagers have tried
digging for years.
ふぅ～。
本気なの？
あぁ 水さえ出れば→
And they've never found water.
I already told him that.
みんな神樹に頼らなくていいだろ。
But once he gets an idea,
he just won't listen.
無理だわ 村の人たちも
何年もかけて掘ったのよ。
It doesn't matter whether
it's possible or not.
でも 水は出なかった。
I've decided to do it.
俺も そう言ったさ。
See you, Kanna.
でも 言い出すと聞かないんだよ
こいつは。
できるか できないかは 関係ない。
Are you two... stupid?
俺は やるって決めたんだ。
I might be...
But he definitely is.
じゃあな カンナ。
あんたたち… バカなの？
俺はともかく
あいつは間違いない。
Even if it takes years,
I'll make it happen.
《何年かかろうと やり遂げる》
I've returned.
Welcome back.
How did it go?
I did exactly as I was told.
(インドラ)ただいま戻りました。
Were there any problems?
No.
Peace has returned to the village.
よく戻った。 で 首尾は？
Lord Hagoromo...
万事 仰せのとおりに。
Master Indra has returned first.
何か問題は？
Which means the successor
of Ninshu is...
ありません。
村には平穏が戻りました。
No, I'm not interested in
how fast things were resolved.
ハゴロモ様
インドラ様が先に戻られました。
I will wait for Ashura to return.
ということは 忍宗の後継者は…。
Then I will decide.
Is that all right, Indra?
いいや わしは
物事の速さを問うたのではない。
Yes.
アシュラの帰りを待つ。
決めるのは それからだ。
よいな インドラ。
はい。
It's been awhile, Indra.
Oh?
You're in a bad mood.
Didn't you come to see me?
I'm aware of everything, you know.
(ゼツ)久しぶりだね インドラ。
You did exactly as Hagoromo wished.
But he's still not satisfied.
あれ？ ノリが悪いね。
僕に会いにきたんじゃないの？
The future Hagoromo envisions for
Ninshu is not the future you envision...
僕には全部わかってるよ。
キミは ハゴロモの望むとおりにした。
でも満足はしていない。
ハゴロモの思い描く忍宗の未来は
キミの思い描く未来じゃない。
You've improved.
No matter what happens,
the two of us will follow you, Indra.
I will remember your words.
腕を上げたな。
俺たち２人は
どんなことがあろうと→
Lord Hagoromo...
It's been one year since Master Ashura
set out on his journey.
インドラ お前についていくぜ。
その言葉 胸に刻んでおく。
But he still hasn't returned.
Your pupils are becoming restless.
ハゴロモ様 すでに アシュラ様が
旅立って１年になります。
Perhaps, you should
decide on a successor...
I realize that.
しかし いまだ
アシュラ様は戻ってきません。
No one will object to Master Indra.
弟子たちの動揺もあります。
Why do you insist on waiting
for Master Ashura?
そろそろ後継者を決められては。
Don't worry.
Ashura will return soon.
それは わかっている。
インドラ様なら
誰も文句を言いますまい。
Lord Hagoromo!
What's going on?
なぜに アシュラ様の帰りを？
Master Indra!
心配するな。
そろそろアシュラも戻ってくる頃だ。
Master Ashura has returned!
ハゴロモ様！
なにごとだ？
インドラ様！
Hey!
アシュラ様が… お帰りになりました。
It's not just Master Ashura!
There are so many with him!
I recognize Taizo,
but who are the others?
So he's back.
お～い！
You are astute about your own sons.
アシュラ様だけではないぞ。
あんなに大勢？
タイゾウはわかるが
他の者は 何者なのだ？
I think this water jar
has seen its day.
戻ってきたか。
(ガマ丸)自分の息子のことは
よくわかるのぉ。
My, my, it took a long time.
The younger one is very clumsy...
う～ん この水がめも
そろそろ限界かの。
But his tenacity
is quite something.
I told you to mind
your own business.
いやいや 時間がかかった。
I didn't do anything.
弟のほうは
とんでもなく不器用じゃな。
I just watched, that's all.
根性は たいしたものじゃが。
But I want to let you in
on something.
余計なことはするなと
念を押したはずだぞ。
About the village Indra went to.
しておらん。
ただ ずっと眺めとっただけじゃ。
Welcome back.
It's great to be home.
Have you been well?
それより お前の耳に
入れておきたいことがある。
Yes. I'm glad you're well too,
Master Ashura.
インドラの里のことじゃ。
Please go and see Lord Hagoromo.
What? Didn't he decide on
Elder Brother already?
おかえりなさいませ。
ただいま。 元気だったか？
Is Father still?
はい。 アシュラ様こそ よくご無事で。
He's been waiting all this time
for your return, Master Ashura.
さあ 早くハゴロモ様に。
えっ 兄さんに決まったんじゃ…。
I see...
まだ 父上は…。
ずっと アシュラ様の帰りを
待っておられました。
そうなのか。
Father, I've returned.
You've become very dignified,
Ashura.
We got tired waiting for you...
Forgive me Elder Brother.
父上 ただいま戻りました。
With the level of my strength,
I needed much longer to resolve
the problem in the village.
凛々しくなったな アシュラ。
Who are those people?
待ちわびたぞ。
Oh, yes.
申し訳ありません 兄さん。
These are some of the villagers.
They all helped me.
俺の力では 行った村の問題を
解決するには→
And are now valuable friends.
長い時間が必要でした。
We heard about this village,
and we wanted to see it,
その者たちは？
あっ はい。 村の方々です。
so we accompanied Master Ashura.
みんなが俺を助けてくれました。
I see.
Welcome, good of you to come.
今では大事な仲間です。
Ashura, let me hear your story.
この里の話を聞き
どうしても この目で見たくて→
The village I went to relied on
the Divine Tree's water source.
アシュラさんとともにまいりました。
So I decided to dig a well.
そうか。 よくいらした。
アシュラ 話を聞こう。
Ashura! Are you seriously
digging a well?
俺の行った村は
神樹の水源に頼っていました。
It's what I've decided.
そこで
井戸を掘ることにしたんです。
((ハァ ハァ…。
アシュラ 本気で井戸を掘ってるの？
俺は そう決めたんだ。
はぁ～。
What the hell?
Are they back to throw rocks at us?
ふぅ…。
ん？
Wait.
なんだよ… また 俺たちに
石を投げにきたのか!?
待て！
You guys...
We'll help you.
We want to do it because
it's for our village.
If you can,
could you teach us Ninshu too?
あんたたち…。
俺たちも手伝う。
Uh-huh!
自分たちのことくらい
自分でやりたい。
できれば 俺たちにも
忍宗を教えてくれないか？
あ… うん。
Everyone, please be quiet!
What's the matter, Ashura?
Can you hear it?
みんな！ 静かにしてくれ。
That sound...
どうしたんだ？ アシュラ！
聞こえないか？ 音がする！
It's water!
– What is it?
– What happened?
水だ！
どうした!?
This is—!
– Water!
– We hit water!
– We did it!
You did it, Ashura!
We did it!
これって…。
(タイゾウ)やった！ やったぞ!!
やったわ アシュラ！
あぁ やった！
(アシュラ)やった～！
Mom...
Kanna.
Mom!
母さん…。
カンナ。
母さん！
We are finally free from the curse.
今こそ 我々は
長き呪縛より解き放たれる。
I see...
So the Ninshu that you spread
has saved many people.
Yes!
I will now name
the successor to Ninshu.
そうか… お前の広めた忍宗が
人々を救ったか。
はい！
The one who shall
take over Ninshu shall be...
では これより
忍宗の後継者を発表する。
忍宗の後継者は…。
boku ni wa wakaru nda uso o tsuite iru kimi ga
I can tell when you're lying
naite ii yo koko ni zutto irukara
It's okay to cry because I'll always be here
sekaijuu ni koborete iru hontou no ai no kimochi
Feelings of true love spills out throughout the world
sagashidashite miushinatte yoake ga kuru no matteru
We search for it but lose it, while waiting for daybreak
migi no hoshi ni wa boku no namae o tsukete
The star on the right will bear my name
kimi ga yonde okureyo
Will you call out to it?
hidari no hoshi ni wa kimi no namae ga ne
The star on the left will bear your name
niau yo zutto soba ni irukara
It's perfect, because we'll always be together
Bonds allow people to share
in each other's joy and sorrow.
In the beginning, bonds overflow
with love and emotion.
As long as there are bonds,
Ninshu will not be used for evil.
But power without bonds will surely
bring calamity to this world.
Next time on Naruto Shippuden:
The Successor
From here on out,
I entrust my power to you.